Rhiannon: A mental health crisis
is an emergency that poses a
direct and immediate threat to
physical or emotional wellbeing.
There is no one set definition of
what a crisis entails, as it is
highly personal to each individual.
Leah: A mental health crisis in children
and young people, is usually when
they show signs of being extremely
anxious, having panic attacks,
feeling suicidal or self-harming.
They may also show signs of feeling very
high, or having a very low mood, or even
suffering from episodes of psychosis.
Rhiannon: They may be facing extreme
challenges in their life, such as
bereavement, financial problems
within the family, family break-up,
exam stress or housing problems.
They may also already have
a mental health diagnosis.
Or they may have challenges that
are not obvious, which may just be
affecting their mental well-being.
Leah: How do you plan for something like
a mental health crisis, especially if
you hope it won’t happen or have no idea
about the possibility it might happen?
As in any health crisis the first place
to go is Accident & Emergency [999] by
phone or directly at the local hospital.
Also, emergency GP appointments are
available, even if not registered
and if talking is needed, there
are multiple helplines available.
Rhiannon: There is always an option and an
answer, so make sure to stay aware of what
these are and how to make use of them.